Now one of the things that people are very
much confused by in the modern world is what
archaic people meant by gods, and that’s
because whatever the deities were that had
the motive force that archaic people attributed
to the gods seemed to have disappeared in
modern culture. Now the Jungian in hypothesis
is that’s because they turned into psychological
traits, fundamentally, or motivational forces,
so what the, what archaic societies would
describe as gods, we would describe as motivational
forces,
so, for example, Venus is a goddess, the goddess
of love, and we would associate her power
with love and sex fundamentally, and the reason
that that’s a reasonable association from
the archaic standpoint is because the motive
quality that makes up what Venus represents
is transpersonal, which means it’s not limited
to one person and it’s immortal in that
the motive force that characterizes sexual
affiliation exists whether or not a single
individual exists.
so it’s transpersonal, has the force of
a personality , because, if you fall in love,
you’re motivated by a certain set of standards
and perspectives, right, if you’re gripped
by beauty, say, or if you’re gripped by
lust, that imposes a particular view of the
world on you and impels your actions, sometimes
despite your will, and so that would be equivalent,
from the archaic perspective, to possession.
And it’s clearly the case that archaic societies
who are engaged in warfare, for example, would
conduct rituals to ensure that the warriors
that made up their societies were, in fact,
possessed by the correct god, so it might
be Mars, for example, the Roman God of War,
so that on the battlefield they exhibited
the proper characteristics of somebody who
was in a battle, right, rage you can think,
rage, so possession by the God of War would
be equivalent to this possession by a state
of rage
Now, it’s not quite that simple, it isn’t
only that archaic people externalized motive
forces and gave them the status of deities,
what they did was more complex than that,
and I think you can understand that a little
bit better if you start to, if you start to
give some, uh, thought to the modern behavioral
notion of the stimulus.
Now the stimulus is a very, very weird concept,
because the behaviourists who were interested
in taking apart what was inside the brain
would attribute motive force to the stimulus,
right, they’d say, if you present an animal
with a stimulus, he will therefor act, and
that meant that the behaviours were making
the presupposition that the motive power resided
in some manner in the stimulus. Well and why,
why would they think like that?
Well, it’s an archaic mode of thought in
a sense. You can imagine a child saying, um,
one of my friends today made me really angry,
right, which means that the child is essentially
conflating his or her own internal emotional
state with the proximal stimulus that gave
rise to that state, and you see complex associations
like that taking place with regards to the
apprehension of beauty, say, because beauty
is a very, very complex and difficult to localize
phenomena; if you’re very attracted to someone,
are you attracted by them? Well in a sense,
of course, you are, because there they are,
but in another sense you’re not at all because
what’s happening is that you’re engaged
as much in the in attraction as anything that’s
motivating you from the outside world, and
I think that partly accounts for your sense
of foolishness, especially if the person that
you’re attracted to doesn’t return your
attraction,
I mean, you, you know that from your perceptual
perspective you’re attracted and dominated
by the object, but, uh, by the same token,
you know entirely that, easy as it is to presume
it’s them and their fault, say, pretty much
it all has to do with you, so in the modern
world where we’ve been able to separate
out the object and the motive force of the
object, the deities have sort of moved inside
of us and become psychological forces, but
you can understand if you think about it in
this manner that things weren’t so clear
prior to the dawn of the empirical age,
that gives you a little bit of background
with regards to what the notion of deity meant
to archaic societies who still utilize those
notions as explanatory terms. Okay, so we
know that if you’re caught up in one of
these little, uh, world games, that you may
be motivated by something very, very fundamental,
right, a, a tendency that transcends you the
tendency to propagate yourself, say, Freud’s
fundamental motivational level, sexual affiliation
or the tendency to maintain yourself, those
you could say are the fundamental gods of
existence, the fundamental driving forces,
and it’s there, it’s the interaction of
those two forces over great periods of time
that produce the great diversity of life and,
and human life, that we see before us, and
each of those fundamental, most fundamental
of gods, have their differentiated minion
so to speak so that while engaged in the meta
goal of self preservation, you act out plots
of hunger and plots of thirst and you move
from cold to hot or from hot to cold depending
on your particular, uh, on your particular,
on the particular temperature of your surroundings
or with regards to self propagation.
You’re attracted to people or are repelled
by them for reasons that are frequently absolutely
beyond your comprehension by the way, so I
just found out this week, uh, and this is
absolutely staggering, I think, that if you,
um, if you run an experiment on a group of
women and you track their menstrual cycle,
and then you give them t-shirts that men have
worn to smell, that women who are ovulating
like the smell of symmetrical men better than
A-symmetrical men, so and that’s partly
because symmetrical men are probably more
healthy, but this is a good example of how
the motive forces that configure your world
are dependent on instinctual forces that are
not only beyond your consciousness, but they’re
beyond even, at the moment, any of our, uh,
explicit explanations.
So, uh, another finding that’s very similar
that I came across recently, it turns out
that mice will not mate with mice that have
RH blood factors that are likely to produce,
um, unfit offspring, uh, the more closely
genetically related the RH factors, the more
likely there is to be a, a, an, a catastrophe
with regards to offspring, and the mice seem
to detect the RH factor by smell so recently
this was run by, with women, and it is also
the case that women prefer men whose RH factors
are at an optimal distance from them in terms
of smell, so this is some example of how these
unbelievably archaic systems, ‘cause like
the old factory systems are unbelievably archaic,
produce alterations in world view at a level
that’s massively below consciousness, so
underneath your cortical shell, which is tonically
inhibiting all your emotional and motivational
systems, lies all these motivational and emotional
systems, and they have branches that grow
up into the cortex, and they have the capacity
to control your behaviour completely and voluntarily,
so, for example, if you’re gripped by fear,
if you’re gripped by fear, it’s very,
very difficult to overcome that voluntarily,
and at least initially you won’t be able
to, which is to say that when the chips are
down, the underlying motivational and emotional
systems have control. Okay. So then what happens
from that perspective, then what happens when
you encounter something you don’t understand,
and I think the best way to explain it is
something like generalize disinhibition, which
is that all your underlying motivational and
emotional systems are more or less disinhibited
simultaneously, and the reason for that is
because you want to be maximally prepared
to do whatever the hell is necessary to do
when you are somewhere that you don’t understand,
and because you don’t know what that thing
is going to be, all your systems go on, and
when psychologists talk about stress, which
is an abysmal word, right, it means everything
and nothing, when psychologists talk about
stress, what they mean is, generalized disinhibition
of emotion and motivation
so then you come to the case of ancient Egypt
And one of the things Eliade points out, which
I think is really interesting, I mean really
phenomenal, the story I’m going to tell
you right now was essentially revealed in
Egyptian culture at the dawn of the culture
rather than developing over the course of
the culture. So the Egyptians had a revelation,
right, immediately that the most fundamental
of gods was the one who created as a consequence
of his tongue and his speech, very much akin
to the Sumerian idea with regards to Marduk
and also to later Judao-Christian ideas.
so here’s the story. There’s four players
in this drama, OK? There’s Osiris, his wife
Isis, Horace their son, and Seth. And Seth
is Osiris’ evil brother, OK? Now Osiris
was a remarkable guy. He was the founder of
the Egyptian state from the mythological perspective,
so kind of like Romulus and Remus for Rome,
a myth or like George Washington for the U.S.,
right? A mythologized figure who represented
all of the Pharaohs and people for that matter
who’d actually constructed the Egyptian
state.
Osiris, father of Egypt, so to speak, but
Osiris is kind of old and a little archaic
and maybe a little bit senile and even possibly
a little bit naïve in that you know even
no matter how great you were in your youth,
as time goes on you lose contact with environmental
transformations and the old rules that you
lived by are not necessarily applicable to
the present and some of those things that
you ignore become paramount in importance.
And it turns out that Osiris has an evil brother,
Seth, and Seth eventually turns into Satan
as mythology develops through the centuries.
And Seth is a nasty guy, right, I mean what
he wants more than anything is undeserved
dominion over the Egyptian state. Now Osiris,
because he’s not paying attention and because
he isn’t sufficiently cognizant anymore
of the power of evil, more or less ignores
his evil brother, who in turn chops him into
pieces and then distributes his pieces all
over the Egyptian state. Now you might say:
why didn’t he just kill him, right? I mean
you’d think chopping him up would kill him
but he’s a god, you can’t just kill them.
The reason in mythology, and you see this
in movies as well, where the villain never
quite dies or the hero never quite dies, is
because even if you eliminate individual embodiments
of what those figures represent, new embodiments
manifest themselves virtually immediately.
So one of the things mythology is quite clear
about is that you never win a final battle
with evil. It’s a permanent property of
the world.
So anyways, Seth hacks up Osiris, spreads
him all over the land. Osiris ends up living
a kind of shadowy and nebulous ghost-like
existence down in the underworld and Seth
becomes the ruler of the state. A nasty story.
Alright, but Osiris has Isis as a wife. Now
Isis had a huge cult. She was a powerful goddess,
goddess of the under world, a kind of combination
of Kali and Diana, so to speak, capable of
tremendous destructive power but also the
source of all good things – something very
much like Tiamat. Now Isis got wind of her
husband’s disintegration, so to speak, and
she went searching around Egypt till she found
his phallus and with it she makes herself
pregnant.
OK, so what does that mean exactly? It means
something like this. The collapse of any great
order brings with it new potential and I think
this is something that capitalism has way
over forms of government like communism. Capitalism
has mechanisms in place to allow large structures
that are no longer meeting their function
to collapse. But frequently when they collapse,
it’s not like they disintegrate into dust,
right, they disintegrate into sub-components,
so to speak, many of which then come to terms
with the fact that the order has collapsed
and build something new. So you can’t get
rid of culture so easily. You can hack it
up into bits, you can disembody it, so to
speak, you can spread it all over the state,
you can introduce chaos into it. But that’s
something that has the potential of new birth
like the phoenix rising from the ashes.
So anyways, Isis, who’s the matrix, who’s
Tiamat, gets Osiris’ phallus, which is the
container of the germ of culture, right, the
phenomenon that’s capable of the seminal
idea, and she makes herself pregnant and she
gives birth to Horace, who’s the long-lost
son of the rightful king, right, a very typical
mythological motif. OK, so Horace is alienated
from the kingdom, which is another very common
mythological motif, you know like how King
Arthur, for example, is raised by commoners?
The same story pops up in the story for Christ,
for example, because Christ has heavenly parents
but then he also has kind of ordinary parents
and it’s a very common motif. Anyways, so
Horace grows up outside of the classical structure
of the Egyptian state, which is tilted terribly
towards evil because Seth has dominated, because
Osiris was too blind to his evil brother to
take appropriate defensive actions, and he
grows to maturity. And then he decides, like
all rightful sons of the long-lost king, to
reclaim his heritage. So he goes back to Egypt,
right, and he has this vicious battle with
Seth and in the process, Seth tears out one
of his eyes. Well, fine, and that’s an indication
of just exactly how devastating a battle with
the forces of evil, so to speak, precisely
are. They represent a critical threat to the
integrity of consciousness, right? That’s
why he loses an eye. Well, luckily enough,
Horace has got his act together and he does
defeat Seth and he banishes him and he gets
the eye back. And then you think: OK, great,
pop the eye back in, become emperor, everything’s
fine
Now let’s backtrack a little bit and think
about this politically. Now the Egyptians
had this really weird idea. They had the idea
that the living pharaoh was the living pharaoh
and the dead pharaoh at the same time. makes
no sense rationally but it makes a lot of
sense from a narrative perspective because
what they were saying is something like this:
look, you got to think that when you become
king, or when you become president, or when
you take on a role of that absolute magnitude,
that then you’re partly you but you’re
also partly this role and there’s really
no way out of that, right? And the role is
composed of the unbelievable weight of the
cultural tradition that you’re representing.
And you can say: well, that’s true for being
king or for being president but it’s also
true if you become a doctor or a lawyer, any
sort of specialized occupation. It’s partly
you, because you’re embodying the role,
but it’s partly the role too. So the pharaoh
is the live pharaoh and the dead pharaoh because
the dead pharaoh represents culture, right?
The king is dead, long live the king.
OK, but paralleling that idea was the idea
that the pharaoh was not only the dead pharaoh
and the live pharaoh at the same time but
that he was Osiris and Horace at the same
time. But then you think in the story, Horace
has taken over Seth, he’s got his eye back,
he can be king. But he isn’t king yet and
this is where the Egyptians really get their
act together and I think, of the two stories
that I’m telling you, this is the one that
has the most significance, I think, for modern
people because we’re so likely to sidestep
our obligation to our culture, whatever that
happens to be. So instead of popping this
eye back in his head, which is the first thing
you’d think he does, he decides he’s going
to go back to the underworld, where Osiris
is living in this ghostlike and dead manner,
since he’s been chopped up by Seth. So he
goes down into the underworld, which is no
piece of cake, and he finds Osiris there in
this kind of half-dead state and he gives
him his eye. And that enlightens Osiris, right,
it gives him vision and so then he takes Osiris
back to Egypt arm in arm, so to speak. And
it’s the conjunction of Osiris and Horace
that constitutes the basis for Egyptian sovereignty
and that is bloody brilliant, right, because
the Egyptians figured out that so Horace is
Marduk, for all intents and purposes, right?
He’s this avenging hero. In the Egyptian
story, he fights political corruption rather
than chaos but you can understand that those
are two flipsides of the hero archetype, they
are.
The hero archetype has two basic elements.
One is the confrontation of the terrible aspect
of nature, chaos in its most brutal form,
and the other is the confrontation with the
archaic aspect of culture. And in some ways,
those aren’t distinguishable because if
culture isn’t archaic, chaos never makes
itself present. So which is to say you can’t
separate out political degradation from environmental
degradation, say, it’s the same idea.
So anyways, Horace has this great idea. He
needs his father, right, and I told you about
the same motif emerging in Pinocchio, we already
looked at that, right? Pinocchio doesn’t
become genuine until he risks his life saving
his father, alright, so the same thing is
happening in this particular situation. So
that’s pretty cool. So then you get the
situation where the Egyptians characterize
sovereignty as the capability to overcome
evil in the political domain, combined with
– and that’s a youthful capability, right
– combined with the wisdom of the past,
alright? Then you look at that from a political
perspective and you find out already that
the Egyptians viewed the pharaoh as the live
pharaoh and the dead pharaoh simultaneously.
But then you find out something else that’s
interesting and it gives you some real insight
into just exactly how bloody powerful these
ideas were. So you think: what did the Egyptians
do with their spare time? And then you think:
well, they built the pyramids, right, I mean
and that was no trivial undertaking. It was
sort of the 5000 B.C. equivalent of flying
to Mars. And I mean the pyramids are pretty
impressive now but they were a hell of a lot
more impressive in their original form because
they were in the middle of an immense complex.
And the pyramids were dedicated to the immortality
of the pharaoh and the pharaoh was possessed
by a spirit called Ka and Ka was his immortal
spirit and it was the union of Horace and
Osiris, OK?
So Egyptian society was dedicated to deifying
the immortal spirit of the pharaoh, the union
of Horace and Osiris. And it was the union
that gave the, it was this identification
with this union that gave the pharaoh a phenomenon
the Egyptians called Maat and Maat was like
truth or good order. And you could think about
it as conscience in a sense is if the pharaoh
was utilizing the union of Horace and Osiris,
then he would have an intuitive ability to
decide what the appropriate course of order
was. And so the Egyptians would say, for example,
when the pharaoh came into the court, they’d
say: the sun has risen by that they meant
the power that reigned over the dominion of
the night had arrived. They conceptualized
maat as the capacity to put order in the place
of chaos, essentially formally. So they assimilated
the union of Horace and Osiris with the capability
of putting order in the face of chaos. They
regarded that as immortal and they spent all
of the excess resources of their society glorifying
that idea. And you think: you don’t produce
something like the pyramids without really
being possessed by an idea, right? This is
no trivial undertaking, it’s going over
a period of several hundred, if not several
thousand, years. That takes an awful lot of
work. So this idea of the immortality of the
union of Horace and Osiris and its association
with sovereignty was an absolutely potent
idea for the Egyptians. It gave their whole
culture motive force.
OK, so the Egyptians thought: the pharaoh
is immortal and that’s the reason why and
we more or less partake in his immortality
by being his subjects. So that was a pretty
good deal. But then Eliade points out something
very interesting and this is called the democratization
of Osiris and what you found was that initially
there were certain symbolic presentations
representing the immortality of the pharaoh
that could only be used by the pharaoh. But
as Egyptian culture continued to develop,
then the symbolic representations of immortality
started to be adopted by the aristocracy.
Now what did that mean? It meant that this
process that the Egyptians had conceptualized
as integral to the order of the state was
no longer solely embodied in the hands of
the pharaoh, right? It had started to drift
down the power hierarchy into the aristocracy,
OK? Well then you think: what happens after
that? So by the end of Egyptian society, the
aristocrats were characterized by an identity
with the union of Horace and Osiris, right?
Sovereignty had started to spread itself out.
And you think: what starts to happen with
the Greeks, right? The Greeks attribute sovereignty
to every male Greek. Barbarians, no. Women,
no. But at least all males, right? You get
a beginning of a democratic notion there.
The Jews developing ideas that, if not derived
from Egypt, were at least similar in structure
to Egyptian ideas, say: not the aristocracy,
not the pharaoh but every individual has the
capacity of establishing a direct relationship
with the transcendent deity, right? Then you
have a Christian revolution that follows that
where the idea that sovereignty inheres in
the individual, is distributed to everyone,
right, everyone – male, female, criminal,
non-criminal, murderer, rapist, taxman, you
name it, sovereignty inheres within them.
And it’s on that soil that our whole democratic
culture emerges – these unbelievably archaic
ideas, first acted out, right, first embodied
in ritual, first dramatized then only told
as stories, developing more and more coherence
over stretches of time of thousands of years,
not hundreds of years but thousands of years,
becoming more coherent, becoming more pointed,
becoming more relevant with regards to their
embodiment, then starting to become understood
explicitly and distributed to the entire society.
And it’s on that ground that our world rests,
not on the ground of rationality, as established
in say Europe in 1500. What we have is much
more profound and solid and deep than any
mere rational construction. It’s a from
of government, an equilibrated state, so to
speak, that’s a consequence of an emergent,
if not evolutionary, at least social evolutionary
process. And I would say that it stems much
farther back than that because you can imagine
something like this. Look, if this ideal personality
that should be sovereign is represented by
the optimal combination of creativity and
traditionalism, say, if that’s the optimal
combination, and if we’re prepared to regard
that as optimal, if that’s a – if that’s
what you perceive when you perceive someone
that you respect and admire, then you could
say that success in our social hierarchies
is predicated on the degree to which you actually
embody that combination. And then you see
an interaction between individual success
and the social construction that would be
an interaction that extends over centuries
or even thousands of centuries so that as
these ideas become more and more developed,
we become more and more adapted to embodying
them as a consequence of evolutionary pressure.
So it’s not just cultural, it’s also biological.
So our political presuppositions rest on a
cultural basis which is unbelievably archaic,
resting in turn on something even lower than
that. And I think examples of that are those
that I’ve provided you with already. We
know, for example, that chimps who have to
live in a dominance hierarchy are very aggressive,
especially the males, but they’re also very
cooperative. So the males who are aggressive
spend a substantial amount of time repairing
social boundaries in the aftermath of an aggressive
incident because they’re just as concerned
with keeping the bloody hierarchy intact as
they are in climbing it. They have to be.
And we know that even wolves won’t kill
a subordinate wolf once they’ve defeated
it. They allow the subordinate wolf to maintain
its own existence, right, they have this notion,
this procedural notion that – even those
entities that appear insignificant may, in
some manner that’s beyond speech, still
contribute to the integrity of the whole.
And that’s an idea that’s very much similar
to our notion that sovereignty inheres in
the individual, right? We’ve taken it further.
No matter what you do, even if you’re in
clear violation of the law, your rights remain
intact because no matter how outcast you are
and how apparently beyond redemption, your
existence may still contribute something to
the integrity of the whole. And as far as
I’m concerned, that doesn’t appear to
be a metaphorical idea. If you dismiss it,
you cannot dismiss it without simultaneously
dismissing the ground on which our states
rest. And so then you have to ask yourself:
are you willing to do that? And if the answer
is no, well then you have to start to question
what it is that you actually believe, because
if you buy the doctrine of natural rights,
which you do, you act it out, then all of
this follows in its wake, or it rests on sand.
And it bloody well better not rest on sand.